Let's move now to access methods. So how to
access files and which is the minimum unit
we can read or write from secondary storage
or the disk so we can go in two ways here one is
sequential access.
So the idea is that
we start reading a file from the very beginning
and then we have functionality that allows
us to
take the next
let's say piece of information in the file,
we will see this is called block, or to go
back. So it's like scanning a file. This could
be a way to access the information in a file
and the operating system can give you
functionality to do this sequential read.
But we can also have direct access, so we
might want functionality that allows us to
read or write at specific offsets in the file, so that
we can rapidly go where we want instead of
just scanning everything it depends on the
type of file. If you have to
listen to a song that is in a file, then most
likely you are going to scan everything because
you have to read the entire file in order.
If you are accessing a data file and you only
need to take some specific data values and
you know how the file is organized like a
matrix, maybe then you can go in a specific
offset and read the stuff.
Now, independently of which one of the two
we use,
the operating system reasons in terms of blocks.
So whether we read one thing after the other or
we access something at a specific position,
the minimum unit we can use to interact with
the disk is called block, which is a group
of or
a certain amount of bytes, as you can imagine. So why
do we read blocks instead of just bites? Why
don't we go "give me the next byte" or "give
me / go to a specific byte"? Remember
this is not inside the memory. This is when
we actually want to read something from the
disk.
Well, you remember this. We saw some lectures
ago that whenever you have to read or write
something from the disk, the CPU cannot directly
communicate with the disk, it needs to go through
several cycles because as we said, the CPU
only reaches main memory directly, which means
we will have system calls, context switches,
we have to move processes in a waiting
queue
we need to wait for the input output of the
disk, interrupts and so on, so you can imagine
that pay all this price every time you need
a byte and you have to read a very large file it
doesn't really make sense, right? it's
too much overhead.
So instead what we do is that if we read or
write something, then we take a chunk of the
file, because similar in spirit to the concept
of locality. You know that if you need a certain
byte most likely you also need bites that are
around that one.
So now the question is:
fine, let's use blocks instead of bytes, how
big should a block be?
If the minimum unit, the block, is all you
can read or write and you choose a very large
block. The good thing is that you don't need
to read or write a lot of blocks when you
have to store or read something, on the other
end, if a block is let's say 1 megabyte and
you want only to write a file that takes a
couple of bites,
then you're going to waste a big chunk
of that block because you can only write blocks.
On the other hand, if you use small blocks,
you can better utilize the disk because you
waste less space, but then you need to read
or write or access in general more blocks
when you have to do something with a file.
And actually, you can see that, as always,
this tradeoffs
result in different behaviors. So in this
graph here you have different block sizes
from one kilobyte to 1 megabyte, and then
you have to lines. The solid one is the disk
space.
and the dashed one is the data rate. So what are we seeing
here? If you look at the data rate, which
is the
dashed one you see that
the larger the block
the higher the data rate.
So basically you can go up to 60 megabytes
per second if you have blocks of 1 megabyte.
Depends of course on what disk you use its own
speed and so on, but the idea is that this
will grow, but on the other hand, if you have
small blocks, and need to read a lot of them,
then the data rate will decrease because you
have to do more context switches and so, on
the other hand, if you look at the disk space,
which is the solid one, you see that if you
have very small blocks
which means you don't waste blocks when you
have to write small amounts of bytes,
you can use almost the entire disk to
actually store the information you want, but
if you start having large blocks,
then there are good chances that you will
waste space in these blocks and the total
disk utilization will go rapidly through towards
the 0%.
Don't get confused here. You are utilizing the disk at 100%, if you
write all the blocks but you are not really
utilizing 100% of the disk because many of these
blocks do not really contain or their content
is not completely related to what you're writing
is just wasted space because you have to write
a MB despite the fact that you actually just
need a couple of bites for that.
So tradeoffs as always and one of the complicated
things here, we already mentioned this also
for memories that if you know
what is the average size of your file, then
you can probably take the best decision to
maximize space utilization while having still
a good data rate, but you cannot really take
such a decision in advance because when you
design the file system you don't know yet
what files will be stored. That depends on
the user and how he uses the computer, and
so on and so forth, which of course complicates
even more the
matter here.
This is just a question I just answered.
So why is it challenging to choose the right
block size? Because you don't know in advance
what the user will actually store on the disk.